John "Jack" M. Chapel

in john-jack-chapel | ⊕ jackchapel.com | ✓ chapel@usc.edu

Summary

I am an applied microeconomist with a decade of experience conducting social science research in academic and public sector settings. I enjoy collaborating with multidisciplinary teams, working on a diverse portfolio of projects, and implementing rigorous, quantitative research designs to inform program and policy improvements.

Fields of Interest: Applied Microeconomics, Health, Labor, Public Policy Citizenship: U.S.

EDUCATION

Ph.D., Economics, University of Southern California	2019-2024
M.A., Economics, University of Southern California	2019 – 2021
B.S., Economics (with distinction), Tulane University	2011 - 2015

Professional Experience

University of Southern California, Schaeffer Center for Health Policy & Economics	
Postdoctoral Scholar – Research Associate	2024-
U.S. Department of Labor, Chief Evaluation Office	
Summer Fellow	2023

University of Southern California, Center for Economic & Social Research

Research Assistant for Silvia H. Barcellos.	Associate Professor	2022 - 2023
---	---------------------	-------------

Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Division for Heart Disease and Stroke Prevention

Research Fellow (ORISE), Applied Research and Evaluation Branch 2015–2019

Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Office on Smoking and Health

Research Fellow	(ORISE),	Evaluation and	Economics	eams	2015-2019

ICF International

Summer Intern, Public Health Division	2013
Summer Intern, Public Health Division	2012

RESEARCH

In-Progress and Working Papers

Distant Friends with Benefits: Social Spillover Effects from Out-of-State Medicaid Expansions

The Great Migration's Impact on Southern Inequality (with Yi-Ju Hung)

Hidden Hypertension and the Labor Force Participation of Older Americans

Peer-Reviewed Publications

Chapel JM, Currid-Halkett E, Tysinger B. The Urban-Rural Gap in Older Americans' Healthy Life Expectancy.

Journal of Rural Health. 2024;1-11.

Chapel JM, Tysinger B, Goldman DP, Rowe JW. The Forgotten Middle: Worsening health and economic trends extend to Americans with Modest Resources Nearing Retirement. *Health Affairs*. 2023;42(9):1230-1240.

- Shantharam SS, Mahalingam M, Rasool A, Reynolds JA, Bhuiya AR, Satchell TD, **Chapel JM**, Hawkins NA, Jones CD, Jacob V, Hopkins DP. Systematic Review of Patient Characteristics, Intervention Features, and Cost of Self-Measured Blood Pressure Monitoring Interventions with Support. *American Journal of Preventive Medicine*. 2022;62(2):285-298.
- MacLeod KE, Chapel JM, McCurdy M, Minaya-Junca J, Wirth D, Onwuanyi A, Lane RI. The Implementation Cost of a Safety-Net Hospital Program Addressing Social Needs in Atlanta. *Health Services Research*. 2021;56(3):474-485.
- Hawkins NA, Bhuiya A, Shantharam S, **Chapel JM**, et al. A Replicable Approach to Promoting Effective Practices: Translating Cardiovascular Disease Prevention Research. *Journal of Public Health Management and Practice*. 2020;27(2):109-116.
- Zhang D, Ritchey M, Park C, Li J, **Chapel J**, Wang G. Association Between Medicaid Coverage and Income Status on Health Care Use and Costs Among Hypertensive Adults After Enactment of the Affordable Care Act. *American Journal of Hypertension*. 2019;32(10):1030-1038.
- Chapel JM & Wang G. Understanding Cost Data Collection Tools to Improve Economic Evaluations of Health Interventions. Stroke and Vascular Neurology. 2019;4(4).
- Yarnoff B, Khavjou O, Elmi J, Lowe-Beasley K, Bradley C, Amoozegar J, Wachtmeister D, Tzeng J, Chapel JM, Teixeira-Poit S, The Paul Coverdell National Acute Stroke Program Team. Estimating the Costs of Implementing Components of Stroke Systems of Care and Data-Driven Quality Improvement in the Paul Coverdell National Acute Stroke Program. *Preventing Chronic Disease*. 2019;16:190061.
- Chapel JM, Ritchey MD, Zhang D, Wang G. Prevalence and Medical Costs of Chronic Diseases Among Adult Medicaid Beneficiaries. *American Journal of Preventive Medicine*. 2017;53(6 Suppl 2):S143-S154.

PRESENTATIONS, MEDIA, AND OTHER PUBLICATIONS

Conferences and Invited Presentations: (* = coauthor, \dagger = poster)

- 2024: Urban Institute
- 2023: California State University-Long Beach Economics Seminar, USC Applied Microeconomics Seminar, ACAP Social Determinants of Health Learning Collaborative
- 2022: Aging Society Research Network Annual Meeting
- 2021: International Microsimulation Association World Congress (2)
- 2020: Academy Health Annual Research Meeting*, Aging Society Research Network Annual Meeting*
- 2019: American Public Health Association*, Annual Conference on the Science of Dissemination and Implementation in Health*, Society for Applied Anthropology Annual Meeting*, Society for Prevention Research Annual Meeting†
- 2018: CDC Evaluation Day
- 2017: Academy Health Annual Research Meeting[†], Annual Conference on the Science of Dissemination and Implementation in Health*[†], Art & Science of Health Promotion Conference*
- 2016: QCOR* \dagger

Reports: (* = coauthored)

- "Economic Evaluation: Intervention Cost Analysis in Public Health" (2018) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.
- "Best Practices for Cardiovascular Disease Prevention Programs: A Guide to Effective Health Care System Interventions and Community Programs Linked to Clinical Services" (2017) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.*
- "What Could Be Addressed in an Evidence-Informed State Workplace Health Promotion Law?" (2017) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.*

"The Shands Jacksonville Patient-Centered Medical Home Diabetes and Hypertension Self-Management Education Model: Program Costs Summary" (2016) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.

"From Policy to Implementation: Collaborative Drug Therapy Management in an Independent Pharmacy" (2016) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.

"Science-in-Brief synopsis of Do State Community Health Worker Laws Align with Best Available Evidence?" (2016) Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Atlanta, GA.

Honors & Awards

University of Southern California PhD Academy Scholarship and Research Fund small grant; Dornsife/graduate

school fellowship (2 years)

Centers for Disease Control CDC/ATSDR Honor Award for Excellence in Program or Policy Evaluation

(nominated with coauthors)

Tulane University Cum Laude; Dean's List; annual merit-based scholarship

Professional Activities

Teaching: CDC DHDSP 2019 Grantee Workshop, CDC DHDSP Evaluation Coffee Break Webinars, CDC

DHDSP 5-Part Webcast on the Basics of Economic Evaluation, Polygence Tutoring

Membership: American Economic Association, American Society of Health Economists

Referee Service: Health Affairs, Scientific Reports, Public Health Nutrition, BMC Health Services Research,

Journal of Public Health Management and Practice, INQUIRY

SKILLS

Software: Stata, ArcGIS, Matlab, NVivo, Microsoft Office suite (Word, Excel, Powerpoint)

Programming: Stata, R, Python, LaTex, Linux, SQL

Graduate coursework: Applied Econometrics for Program & Policy Evaluation, Big Data Econometrics, Health

Economics, Empirical Analysis of Economic Development, Urban Economics, Industrial Organization, Microeconomics, Macroeconomics, Econometrics, Probability & Statistics,

Political Economy (audit), Labor Economics (audit)